Finding Aid for Barry County Health Dept. records, 1909-1954
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Barry County Health Dept. records 1909-1954
Barry County Health Dept.
2 linear feet, 3 oversize volumes, and 1 oversize folder
8577 Cb 2; CB Outsize; UCBm
Monthly and annual reports, photographs, newspaper clippings, communicable disease record, dangerous disease record, and tuberculosis record.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of Richard Cook (donor no. 3240 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Barry County Health Department was established July 1, 1931 by the county board of supervisors. From the beginning the department was associated with the W.K. Kellogg Foundation, whose charter emphasized "the health, happiness and welfare of children." Originally the department had two budgets. One budget covering basic programs was funded by the county. The other, funded by the Foundation, provided for auxiliary programs that included specialized training to physicians and dentists with emphasis on maternal and child health.
The record group includes annual and monthly reports and minutes of the Michigan Community Health Program and the Hastings Health Service Committee. In addition, there are record books detailing the incidences of communicable diseases, tuberculosis, and "dangerous diseases" in the county. The photograph series includes photographs illustrating department activities. Of interest is an album, 1942, with photos of one-room schools in Barry County.
Subjects:
Barry County (Mich.). Health Dept.; Communicable diseases--Michigan--Barry County.; Health boards--Michigan--Barry County.; Public health--Michigan--Barry County.; Tuberculosis--Michigan--Barry County.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Barry County (Mich.). Health Dept.; Barry County (Mich.)--Schools.; Camps--Michigan--Barry County.; Children.; Classrooms--Michigan--Barry County.; One-room schools.; Public health--Michigan--Barry County.; Rural schools.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Reports and minutes
  - Annual Reports, 1931/1932-1943/1944 (Box 1)
  - Report on the department by students at the University of Michigan, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Monthly Reports, 1944-1950 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the M.C.H.P. (Michigan Community Health Program), 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of the Hastings Health Service Committee, 1938-1941 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Guest books, 1942-1963, 3 volumes (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Schools (Box 1)
  - Cancer education program, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Group, identified (Box 1)
  - Groups, unidentified (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder UCBm)
  - Photograph Album of Barry County Schools, 1942 (Box 2)
- Record book of diseases
  - Communicable Disease Record, 1931-1940 (Box 2)
  - Record of Dangerous Diseases, 1909-1935, 2 volumes (Volume 1)
  - Record of Tuberculosis, 1909-1946 (Volume 2)
- Newspaper clippings
  - 1935-1954 (Box 2)